<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Si-Nguyen Mai</title>
<link>https://singuyenmai.github.io/blog.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://singuyenmai.github.io/blog.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>Welcome to Si-Nguyen Mai&#39;s personal website.</description>
<generator>quarto-1.3.302</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Sun, 03 Mar 2024 19:09:20 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>A chaotic butterfly</title>
  <link>https://singuyenmai.github.io/blog/lorenz_attractor/lorenz_attractor.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<section id="once-upon-a-time" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="once-upon-a-time">Once upon a time</h2>
<p>In 1963, meteorologist Edward Lorenz published a mathematical model for the dynamics of atmospheric convection. The equations are in very simplistic forms, but the resulting behaviour of the system is not. The way that its values change over time is enormously complex, obstructing attempts to predict its future state. Lorenz created the math, but he also discovered it. Following his work was the development of the important Chaos Theory, which covers concepts like Fractals, Predictibility, and Determinism. These names are more familiar to math specialists, but in the more general public, many probably have heard the term “<em>the butterfly effect</em>” at some points in their lives. The Lorenz model is the mother of this concept.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-butterfly" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-butterfly">The butterfly</h2>
<p>The Lorenz system comprises of three dynamic elements, or variables, notated as <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?X"> (rate of convection), <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Y"> (horizontal temperature), and <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Z"> (vertical temperature). The dynamics of these variables then are described by a set of equations called ordinary differential equations (ODE). These equations represent the rates of change of the variables, and they are as follows:</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%5Cfrac%7BdX%7D%7Bdt%7D%20=%20%5Csigma%20(Y%20-%20X)%0A"> <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%5Cfrac%7BdY%7D%7Bdt%7D%20=%20X%20(%5Crho%20-%20Z)%20-%20Y%0A"> <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%5Cfrac%7BdZ%7D%7Bdt%7D%20=%20X%20Y%20-%20%5Cbeta%20Z%0A"></p>
<p>I would not go into the details of the equations, nor why Lorenz designed them to be so, nor how to solve them. I assure you, we can completely move on without them. So let’s now stick with this: <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Csigma">, <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Crho">, and <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cbeta"> are parameters - they are constant, and the solutions of these equations will be the functions describing how the system state, i.e.&nbsp;the variables, change through time - mathematically <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?X(t)">, <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Y(t)">, and <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Z(t)">.</p>
<p>To see the “<em>butterfly</em>”, I added some specifications to the model and in solving the equations: <br> 1. <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Csigma=10">, <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Crho=28">, and <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cbeta=8/3"> <br> 2. The timepoints at which we would like to know the values of <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?X">, <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Y">, and <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Z">. Here, I let them 100,000 timepoints evenly spaced from 0 to 100. <br> 3. The initial condition, which is the system state at the initial timepoint. Here, it is a set of <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?X_%7Bt=0%7D%20=%200.1,%20Y_%7Bt=0%7D=0.0">, and <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Z_%7Bt=0%7D=0.0">.</p>
<p>Ready for the beauty?</p>
<div data-notebook="lorenz_system.ipynb" data-notebook-title="The Lorenz system">
<div class="cell" data-execution_count="2">
<div class="cell-output cell-output-display">
<div id="butterfly2d" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://singuyenmai.github.io/blog/lorenz_attractor/lorenz_attractor_files/figure-html/butterfly2d-output-1.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">… Well, it’s already here.</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p><strong>So, what is this “<em>butterfly</em>” made of?</strong></p>
<p>Technically, what you’re seeing is a 2D plot of <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?X"> against <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Z"> values. I just hid the coordinate axes. Also, while the butterfly appears to be just a single line, but actually, they are 100,000 dots that sit very close together there. If you are able to zoom in, you should see the space between them. Wait, but why 100,000 dots? Remember that I talked about the timepoints? These dots are different “states” of <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?X"> and <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Z"> in time and their varying colors represent this.</p>
<p>Okay. But hey, there are three variables in the system. What it’s like when we also have <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Y"> there?</p>
<p>Let’s see it in 3D. This time, you can also interact with the graph. You can view the system entirely and inspect it from multiple angles. Try holding your pointer on the image, zooming in/out, and turning it around.</p>
<!-- {{< embed lorenz_system.ipynb#butterfly3d echo=false >}} -->
<p align="center">
<iframe width="510" height="420" frameborder="0" seamless="seamless" src="./butterfly3d.html">
</iframe>
</p><figcaption class="figure-caption">
Black dot is the system state at time zero.
</figcaption>
<p>
</p>
</section>
<section id="fractals" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="fractals">Fractals</h2>
<p>The beauty of the butterfly comes from the mix of warm and cold colors in both wings. Can this mix of colors - the colors of time, mean anything? Can you guess?</p>
<!-- The answer is: given that the color gradient represents the change in time and that the two wings indicate two main regions of system state, this colorful image tells us that as time goes, the system state switchs very frequently back and forth between those two regions.  -->
<!-- Sorry, it's such a long sentence. -->
<p>Let’s view the animation below, and follow the black dot that represents the system state.</p>
<!-- {{< embed lorenz_system.ipynb#animation echo=false >}} -->
<p align="center">
<iframe src="https://giphy.com/embed/DRV9v5BSsIz1Lx0xOs" width="480" height="402" frameborder="0" class="giphy-embed" allowfullscreen="">
</iframe>
</p><p>
</p>
<p>The dot moves around in the XYZ space, showing us how the system state changes as time passes.</p>
<p>Following this movement, you shall see that there is a pattern in it - something was repeated again and again.</p>
<p>At first, the system state circles towards the right wing, yet once it lands on this wing, it circles out. <br> The circling goes on for a while until suddenly, the system switches back to the left wing, <br> which then, again, circles out until it moves back to the right wing. <br></p>
<p>This pattern keeps repeating and can go on infinitely!</p>
<p>If you look very carefully, you will notice that although there is a repeated pattern, the system always takes new paths and never it goes back to an old state. Geometrically, this structure is considered as a <em>fractal</em>. (So now you know what the mathematicians are talking about? :D)</p>
</section>
<section id="chaos" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="chaos">Chaos</h2>
<p>The “strange” dynamics described above is a typical example of <em>chaotic behaviours</em>.</p>
<p>In the language of the Mathematicians, <em>chaos</em> is when a system never converges to any specific fixed state (aka <em>stable state</em>), but keeps changing over time and never goes back to a previous state. <em>“No man ever steps in the same river twice.”</em></p>
<p>To see the chaos of the Lorenz system clearer, let’s view separately the changes through time of each variable <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?X">, <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Y">, and <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Z">.</p>
<div data-notebook="lorenz_system.ipynb" data-notebook-title="The Lorenz system">
<div class="cell" data-execution_count="5">
<div class="cell-output cell-output-display">
<div id="xyz" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://singuyenmai.github.io/blog/lorenz_attractor/lorenz_attractor_files/figure-html/xyz-output-1.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>You can see, all the variables fluctuate wildly over time. They never stops changing and there is no certain periodic cycle in their dynamics. <br> Is this behaviour also considered as “<em>chaotic</em>” to you?</p>
</section>
<section id="stability" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="stability">Stability</h2>
<p>Extreme contrast to <em>chaos</em> is <em>stability</em>. But what is <em>stability</em> then?</p>
<p>An example of a <em>stable system</em> is a population of organisms that follows logistic growth.</p>
<p>In this model, the population at first grows exponentially, propbably because the resources are still abundant. However, since resources are limited, the population cannot grow to infinity but is restricted to a limit.</p>
<p>Starting with a very few number of individuals, the population grows very fast in the beginning. But eventually, the growth slows down and then, reaches the limit.</p>
<p>Once the limit for population size is reached, the population experiences no more change and remains <em>stable</em> there. There should be death but you would expect the death and birth rates are equivalent.</p>
<p>The population level at its limit, therefore, is referred as a <em>stable state</em>, or <em>stable attractor</em>. Can you guess why it is called an <em>attractor</em>? (I’ll leave you with the question :D)</p>
<div data-notebook="lorenz_system.ipynb" data-notebook-title="The Lorenz system">
<div class="cell" data-execution_count="6">
<div class="cell-output cell-output-display">
<div id="logistic-growth" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://singuyenmai.github.io/blog/lorenz_attractor/lorenz_attractor_files/figure-html/logistic-growth-output-1.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</section>
<section id="chaotic-but-deterministic" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="chaotic-but-deterministic">Chaotic, but Deterministic</h2>
<p>Considering one big assumption of the Lorenz model, we will see more of its beauty.</p>
<p>First, what the model assumed is that there are certain fixed rules for the changes of atmospheric convection, which, are represented by the ODEs. This assumption is <em>determinism</em>. And in the Lorenz system, those rules are also very simple, However, to what we’ve seen, the system behaviour is extremely complex and the dynamics are “<em>chaotic</em>”. So all of these tell us that, strangely yet beautifully, <strong>chaos can come from determinism</strong> and <strong>complex dynamics/behaviours can come from just simple rules</strong>.</p>
<p>Another way to interpret these is that when we observe and study the outside world, although some systems may appear to behave chaotically and their changes over time may seem so complex, there is still a possibility that such systems are actually determined by some fixed, and perhaps simple, rules. This brings lots more hope to our desire to understand the world 😄. For me, this interpretation is also special because it is similar to the philosophy of the ancient <strong><em>I Ching</em></strong>, or <strong><em>The Book of Changes</em></strong>.</p>
</section>
<section id="determinism-predictibility" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="determinism-predictibility">Determinism &amp; Predictibility</h2>
<p>As <em>chaotic</em> systems do not converge to any fixed stable states, they are sensitive to initial conditions.</p>
<p>Wait, what?</p>
<p>This means, if we change the initial conditions very very slightly, for instance by adding a super tiny variance to just one variable <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?X"> at time zero, then the dynamics will be changed as well.</p>
<div data-notebook="lorenz_system.ipynb" data-notebook-title="The Lorenz system">
<div id="epsilon" class="cell" data-execution_count="8">
<div id="epsilon-1" class="cell-output cell-output-display" data-execution_count="8">
<pre><code>Text(0.0, 1.0, 'time from 0 to 25,000')</code></pre>
</div>
<div class="cell-output cell-output-display">
<div id="epsilon-2" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://singuyenmai.github.io/blog/lorenz_attractor/lorenz_attractor_files/figure-html/epsilon-output-2.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p><em>… work in progress …</em></p>
<!-- Complex dynamics obstruct predictions. It is absolutely certain that if a system is _deterministic_ and defined by a constant set of rules, then we sure can predict its future once we know exactly two things: (1) the rules dictating and (2) the system's current or past states. However, even assuming that we already have the (1) condition, it's still practically impossible to have perfectly precise measurements for the (2) condition. And this, is a problem that comes with predictibilities of _chaotic_ systems. -->
</section>
<section id="the-west-and-the-east" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-west-and-the-east">The West and The East</h2>
<p><em>… work in progress …</em></p>
</section>
<section id="references" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="references">References</h2>
<p>I’ve learned to demonstrate (computationally) the Lorenz system from the following work:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://geoffboeing.com/2016/12/animating-lorenz-attractor-python/" class="uri">https://geoffboeing.com/2016/12/animating-lorenz-attractor-python/</a></li>
<li><a href="https://fromsystosys.netlify.app/2018/07/28/lorenz-attractor-animation-plotly/" class="uri">https://fromsystosys.netlify.app/2018/07/28/lorenz-attractor-animation-plotly/</a></li>
</ul>
<p>Other pieces of introductory articles about strange attractors, the Butterfly effect, and fractals</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://fractalfoundation.org/OFC/OFC-7-1.html/" class="uri">https://fractalfoundation.org/OFC/OFC-7-1.html/</a></li>
<li><a href="https://hypertextbook.com/chaos/strange/" class="uri">https://hypertextbook.com/chaos/strange/</a></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Math</category>
  <guid>https://singuyenmai.github.io/blog/lorenz_attractor/lorenz_attractor.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 03 Mar 2024 19:09:20 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://singuyenmai.github.io/blog/lorenz_attractor/lorenz_butterfly.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="115" width="144"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
